nine THE STRANGEST HOUSE anyone EVER LIVED IN It was the sweetest, most mysterious
looking place anyone could imagine. The high walls which shut it in were covered
with the leafless stems of climbing roses which were so thick that they were matted
together. Mary Lennox knew they were roses because she had seen a great many
roses in India. All the ground was covered with grass of a wintry brown and
out of it grew clumps of bushes which were surely rose bushes if they were
alive. There were numbers of standard roses which had so spread their branches
that they were like little trees. There were other trees in the
garden, and one of the things which made the place look strangest and
loveliest was that climbing roses had run all over them and swung down long
tendrils which made light swaying curtains, and here and there they had
caught at each other or at a far reaching branch and had crept from one
tree to another and made lovely bridges of the themselves. There were neither
leaves nor roses on them now and Mary did not know whether they were dead or
alive, but their thin gray or brown branches and sprays looked like a sort
of hazy mantle spreading over everything, walls, and trees, and even brown grass,
where they had fallen from their fastenings and run along the
ground. It was this hazy tangle from tree to tree which made it all look so
mysterious. Mary had thought it must be different from other gardens which had
not been left all by themselves so long; and indeed it was different from any
other place she had ever seen in her life. "How still it is!" she whispered. "How
still!" Then she waited a moment and listened at the stillness. The robin, who had flown to his
Treetop was still as all the rest. He did not even flutter his wings; he sat
without stirring, and looked at Mary. "No wonder it is still," she whispered again. "I
am the first person who has spoken in here for 10 years." She moved away from the door,
stepping as softly as if she were afraid of awakening someone She was glad that there was
grass under her feet and that her steps made no sounds. She walked under one of the fairy
likee Gra gray arches between the trees and looked up at the sprays and tendrils which formed
them. "I wonder if they are all quite dead,"
she said. "Is it all a quite dead garden? I wish it
wasn't." If she had been Ben Weatherstaff she could have told whether the wood was
alive by looking at it, but she could only see that there were only gray or
brown sprays and branches and none showed any signs of even a tiny Leaf Bud
anywhere. But she was inside the wonderful garden and she could come
through the door under the ivy anytime and she felt as if she had found a world
all her own. The sun was shining inside the four walls and the high arch of blue
sky over this particular piece of mistle seemed even more brilliant and soft than
it was over the mo The robin flew down from his Treetop and hopped about or
flew after her from one bush to another.
He chirped a good deal and had a very busy air, as if he were showing her
things. Everything was strange and silent and she seemed to be hundreds of miles
away from anyone but somehow she did not feel lonely at
all. All that troubled her was her wish that she knew whether all the roses were
dead, or if perhaps some of them had lived and might put out leaves and buds
as the weather got warmer. She did not want it to be a quite dead garden. If it
were a quite alive garden, how wonderful it would be, and what thousands of roses
would grow on every side! Her skipping rope had hung over her
arm when she came in and after she had walked about for a while she thought she
would skip round the whole garden, stopping when she wanted to look at
things. There seemed to have been grass paths here and there, and in one or two
corners there were alcoves of evergreen with stone seats or tall moss covered
flower NS in them. As she came near the second of these alcoves she stopped
skipping. There had once been a flower bed in it, and she thought she saw
something sticking out of the black earth— —some sharp little pale green
points. She remembered what Ben weather staff had said and she knelt down to look at
them. "Yes, they are tiny growing things and they might be crocuses or snow drops
or daffodils," she whispered. She bent very close to them and sniffed the fresh
scent of the damp earth. She liked it very much. "Perhaps there are some other ones
coming up in other places," she said. "I will go all over the garden and
look." She didn't skip, but walked. She went slowly and kept her eyes on the
ground. She looked in the old border beds and among the grass, and after she had
gone round, trying to miss nothing, she had found ever so many more sharp, pale
green points, and she had become quite excited again. "It isn't a quite dead garden," she
cried out softly to herself. "Even if the roses are dead, there are other things
alive." She did not know anything about gardening, but the grass seemed so thick
in some of the places where the green points were pushing their way through
that she thought they did not seem to have room enough to
grow. She searched about until she found a rather sharp piece of wood and knelt
down and dug and weeded out the weeds and grass until she made nice little clear places around
them. "Now they look as if they could breathe," she said, after she had finished with the first
ones. "I am going to do ever so many more.
I'll do all I can see. If I haven't time today I can come
tomorrow She went from place to place, and dug and weeded, and enjoyed herself
so immensely that she was led on from bed to bed and into the grass under the
trees. The ex exercise made her so warm that she first threw her coat off, and
then her hat, and without knowing it she was smiling down onto the grass and the
pale green points all the time. The robin was tremendously busy. He
was very much pleased to see gardening begun on his own estate. He had often
wondered at Ben weather staff Where gardening is done all sorts of
delightful things to eat are turned up with the soil now Now here was this new kind of
creature who was not half Ben's size and yet had had the sense to come into his
garden and begin at once. Mistress Mary worked in her garden
until it was time to go to her midday dinner. In fact, she was rather late in
remembering, and when she put on her coat and hat, and picked up her skipping rope
she could not believe that she had been working 2 or 3
hours. She had been actually happy all the time; and dozens and dozens of the
tiny, pale green points were to be seen in cleared places, looking twice as
cheerful as they had looked before when the grass and weeds had been smothering
them. "I shall come back this afternoon," she said, looking all round at her new
kingdom, and speaking to the trees and the rose bushes as if they heard her.
Then she ran lightly across the grass, pushed open the slow old door and
slipped through it under the ivy. She had such red cheeks and such bright eyes and
at such a dinner that Martha was delighted. "Two pieces of meat and two
helps of rice put in she said. "Eh! mother will be pleased when I tell her what the
skipping ropes done for thee." In the course of her digging with
her pointed stick Mistress Mary had found herself digging up a sort of white
root rather like an onion. She had put it back in its place and patted the earth
carefully down on it and just now she wondered if Martha could tell her what it
was. "Martha," she said, "what are those white roots that look like
onions?" "They're bulbs," answered Martha.
"Lots of spring flowers grow from them the very little ones are snow drops and
crocuses and the big ones are narcissuses and jonquils and Daffy Down
dillies the biggest of all is lies and purple flags hey they are nice dickens's
got a whole lot of them planted in our bitter garden." "Does Dickon know all about them?"
asked Mary, a new idea taking possession of her. "Our Dickon can make a flower grow
out of a brick walk. Mother says he just whispers things out of the
ground." "Do bulbs live a long time time? Would they live years and years if
no one helped them?" inquired Mary anxiously they things as helps
themselves," said Martha. "That's why poor folk can afford to have them If you
don't trouble them most of them will work away underground for a lifetime and
spread out and have little ons There's a place in the park woods here where
there's snow drops by thousands. They're the prettiest sight in
Yorkshire when the spring comes. No one knows when they was first
planted." "I wish the spring was here now," said Mary. "I want to see all the things
that grow in England." She had finished her dinner and gone to her favorite seat on the Hearth
rug I wish— —I wish I had a little spade," she said. "Whatever does thou want a spade
for?" asked Martha, laughing. "Art thou going to take to digging I must tell mother
that, too." Mary looked at the fire and pondered a little. She must be careful if
she meant to keep her secret kingdom. She wasn't doing any harm, but if Mr. Craven
found out about the open door he would be fearfully angry and get a new key and
lock it up forever more She really could not bear that. "This is such a big lonely place
place," she said slowly, as if she were turning matters over in her mind. "The
house is lonely, and the park is lonely, and the gardens are lonely. So many
places seem shut up. I never did many things in India, but there were more
people to look at— —natives and soldiers marching by— —and sometimes bands playing,
and my Aya told me stories. There is no one to talk to here
except you and Ben weather staff And you have to do your work and Ben weather
staff won't speak to me often. I thought if I had a little spade I could dig
somewhere as he does, and I might make a little garden if he would give me some
seeds." Martha's face quite lighted up. "There now!" she exclaimed, "if that
wasn't one of the things mother said. She says, 'There's such a lot of room in that
big place, why don't they give her a bit for herself, even if she doesn't plant nothing but
parsley and radishes? She'd dig and rake away and be right down happy over it
then was the very words she said." "Were they?" said Mary. "How many things she knows, doesn't
she?" "Eh!" said Martha. "It's like she says: 'A woman as brings up 12 children learn
something besides her ABC Children's as good as arithmetic to to set you finding out
things.'" "How much would a spade cost— —a little one?" Mary asked. "Well," was Martha's
reflective answer, "at thit village there's a shop or so and I saw little
garden sets with a spade and a rake and a fork all tied together for two
shillings and they were stout enough to work with, too." "I've got more than that in my purse,"
said Mary. "Mrs. Morrison gave me 5 shillings and Mrs. Medlock gave me some money from Mr.
Craven." "Did he remember thee that much?"
exclaimed Martha. "Mrs. Medlock said I was to have a shilling a week to spend. She gives me
one every Saturday. I didn't know what to spend it on." "My word! that's riches," said Martha
that can buy anything in the world that wants the rent of our cottage is only
one and repent and it's like pulling eye teeth to get it. Now I've just thought of
something putting her hands on her hips.
"What?" said Mary eagerly. "In the shop at TH they sell packages of flower seeds for a penny
each, and our Dickon he knows which is the prettiest ones and how to make them
grow. He walks over to thit many a day just for the fun of it. Does that know
how to print letters?"
suddenly. "I know how how to write," Mary answered. Martha shook her head. "Our
Dickon can only read printing If th could print we could write a letter to
him and ask him to go and buy the garden
tools and the seeds at the same time." "Oh!
you're a good girl!" Mary cried. "You are, really! I didn't know you were so nice. I
know I can print letters if I try. Let's ask Mrs. Medlock for a pen and ink and
some paper." "I've got some of my own," said Martha. "I bought him so I could print a
bit of a letter to mother of a Sunday.
I'll go and get it." She ran out of the room, and Mary stood by the fire and
twisted her thin little hands together with sheer pleasure. "If I have a spade," she whispered,
"I can make the earth nice and soft and dig up weeds. If I have seeds and can
make flowers grow the garden won't be dead at all— —it will come
alive." She did not go out again that afternoon because when Martha returned
with her pen and ink and paper she was obliged to clear the table and carry the
plates and dishes downstairs and when she got into the kitchen Mrs. Medlock was there and told
her to do something, so Mary waited for what seemed to her a long time before she came
back. Then it was a serious piece of work to write to
Dickon. Mary had been taught very very little because her governesses had
disliked her too much to stay with her.
She could not spell particularly well but she found that she could print letters when she
tried. This was the letter Martha dictated to her: My Dear Dickon: This comes hoping to find you
well as it leaves me at present. Miss Mary has plenty of money
and will you go to thit and buy her some
flower seeds and a set of Gard tools to make a flower bed Pick the prettiest
ones and easy to grow because she has never done it before and lived in India
which is different. Give my love to mother and every one of you. Miss Mary is
going to tell me a lot more so that on my next day out you can hear about
elephants and camels and gentlemen going hunting lions and
tigers. "Your loving sister, Martha Phoebe sauby We'll put the money in the
envelope and I'll get the butcher's boy to take it in his cart. He's a great
friend of Dickens said Martha. "How shall I get the things when
Dickon buys them?" asked Mary HEK bring them to you himself. He'll like to walk
over this way." "Oh!" exclaimed Mary, "then I shall see him! I never thought I should see
Dickon." "Does thou want to see him?" asked Martha suddenly she she had looked so
pleased. "Yes, I do. I never saw a boy foxes
and crows loved. I want to see him very much." Martha gave a little start, as if
she suddenly remembered something. "Now to think," she broke out, "to
think of me forgetting that there and I thought I was going to tell you first
thing this morning I asked mother— —and she said she'd ask Mrs. Medlock her own self."
"Do you mean—" Mary began. "What I said Tuesday. Ask her if you might be driven
over to our cottage someday and have a bit of mother's hot oat cake and butter
and a glass of milk." It seemed as if all the interesting
things were happening in one day. To think of going over the Moore in the
daylight and when the sky was blue! To think of going into the cottage which held 12
children! "Does she think Mrs. Medlock would let me go?" she asked, quite
anxiously I she thinks she would. She knows what a tidy woman mother is and
how clean she keeps the cottage." "If I went I should see your mother as well as
Dickon," said Mary, thinking it over and liking the idea very much. "She doesn't
seem to be like the mothers in India." Her work in the garden and the
excitement of the afternoon ended by making her feel quiet and thoughtful.
Martha stayed with her until tea time but they sat in comfortable quiet and talked very
little. But just before Martha went downstairs for the tea tray Mary asked a
question. "Martha," she said, "has the skullery maid had the toothache again
today Martha certainly started slightly. "What makes the ask that?" she
said. "Because when I waited so long for you you to come back I opened the door
and walked down the corridor to see if you were coming. And I heard that far off
crying again, just as we heard it the other night. There isn't a wind today so
you see it couldn't have been the wind." "Eh!" said Martha restlessly they
mustn't go walking about in corridors and listening Mr. Craven would be that
there angry there's no knowing what he'd do." "I wasn't listening," said Mary. "I was
just was waiting for you— —and I heard it.
That's three
times." "My word! There's Mrs. Medlock's bell," said Martha, and she almost ran out of
the room. "It's the strangest house anyone ever lived in," said Mary drowsily, as she
dropped her head on the cushioned seat of the armchair near her. Fresh air, and
digging, and skipping rope had made her feel so comfortably tired that she fell asleep